Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
The National Bank of Canada
www.nasa.gov
Today, we turn to the question of distributive justice.
How should income and wealth and power
power and opportunities be distributed?
According to what principles?
John Rawls offers a detailed answer to that question.
And we're going to examine and assess his answer
to that question today.
We put ourselves in a
position to do so last time
by trying to make sense of why he thinks
that principles of justice are best derived
from a hypothetical contract.
And what matters is that the hypothetical contract
be carried out in an original position of equality
behind what Rawls calls the veil of ignorance.
So that much is clear.
All right, then let's turn to the principles
that Rawls says would be
chosen behind the veil of ignorance.
First he considers some of the major alternatives.
What about utilitarianism?
Would the people in the original position choose to govern,
their collective lives, utilitarian principles,
the greatest good for the greatest number?
No, they wouldn't, Rawls says.
And the reason is that behind the veil of ignorance,
everyone knows that once the veil goes up
and real life begins, we
will each want to be respected
with dignity.
Even if we turn out to
be a member of a minority,
we don't want to be oppressed.
And so we would agree to reject utilitarianism
and instead to adopt as our first principle
equal basic liberties, fundamental
rights to freedom of speech,
freedom of assembly, and freedom of the people.
A new world, a new society, religious liberty,
freedom of conscience, and the like.
We wouldn't want to take the
chance that we would wind up
as members of an oppressed or a despised minority
with the majority tyrannizing over us.
And so Rawls says utilitarianism would be rejected.
Utilitarianism makes the mistake, Rawls writes, of
forgetting, or at least not taking seriously,
the distinction between persons.
And in the original position behind the
veil of ignorance, we would recognize that and
reject utilitarianism.
We wouldn't trade off our fundamental
rights and liberties for any economic advantages.
That's the first principle.
Second principle has to do
with social and economic inequalities.
What would we agree to?
Remember, we don't know whether we're going to
wind up being rich or poor, healthy or
unhealthy.
We don't know what kind of family we're
going to come from, whether we're going to inherit
millions or whether we will
come from an impoverished family.
Okay?
So we might, at first thought, say,
well, let's require an equal distribution of income
and wealth, just to be on the safe side.
But then we would realize that we could
do better than that, even if we're unlucky and
wind up at the bottom.
We could do better if we
agree to a qualified principle of equality.
Rawls calls it the difference principle, a
principle that says only those social and
economic inequalities will be permitted that work
to the benefit of the least well-off.
So we wouldn't reject all inequality of income and wealth.
We would allow some, but the test would be,
do they work to the benefit of everyone, including
those, or as he specifies the
principle, especially those at the bottom.
Only those inequalities would be accepted behind
the veil of ignorance, and so Rawls
argues, only those inequalities that work to
the benefit of the least well-off are just.
We talked about the examples of Michael Jordan
making $31 million a year, of Bill Gates having
a fortune in the tens of billions.
Would those inequalities be
permitted under the difference principle?
Only if they were part of a
system, those wage differentials, that actually work to
the advantage of the least well-off.
Well, what would that system be?
Only if they were part of theigs part of the
difference principle, for example.
Let me hear what you think about Rawls' claim that
these two principles would be chosen behind the veil of ignorance.
Is there anyone who disagrees that they would be chosen?
All right, let's start up in the
balcony if that's all right. Go ahead.
Okay, your argument depends upon us believing that we
would argue and set policy or justice from a bottom,
for the disadvantaged, and I just don't see
from a proof standpoint where we've proven that.
Why not the top?
Right, and what's your name?
Mike.
Mike, all right, good question.
Put yourself behind the veil of ignorance.
Enter into the thought experiment.
What principles would you choose?
How would you think it through?
Well, I would say things like even Harvard's
existence is an example of preaching toward the top
because Harvard takes the top academics.
And I didn't know when I
was born how smart I would be,
but I worked my life to
get to a place of this caliber.
Now, if you'd said Harvard's going to
randomly take 1,600 people of absolutely no qualification,
we'd all be saying, well,
there's not much to work for.
And so what principle would you choose?
In that situation, I would say a merit-based one,
one where I don't necessarily know what I have,
but I'd rather have a system
that rewards me based on my efforts.
So you, Mike, behind the veil of ignorance,
would choose a merit-based system where
people are rewarded according to their efforts.
All right, fair enough.
What would you say? Go ahead.
My question is if the merit-based argument is based
on when everyone is at a level of equality,
where from that position you're rewarded to where you get,
or is it regardless of what advantages you may have?
When you began your education
to get where you are here?
I think the question you're asking is saying,
if you want to look
at whatever utilitarianism policy it is,
do we want to maximize world wealth?
And I think a system that rewards merit
is the one that we've pretty much all established
is what is best for all of us.
Despite the fact that some of
us may be in the second percentile
and some may be in the 98th percentile,
at the end of the day
it lifts that lowest base level,
a community that rewards merit.
And that's effort as opposed to innate differences.
But I don't understand
how you're rewarding someone's efforts
who clearly has had, not you but maybe myself,
advantages throughout to get where I am here.
I mean, I can't say that somebody else
who maybe worked as hard as I did
would have had the same opportunity
to come to a school like this.
All right, let's look at that point. What's your name?
Kate.
Kate, you suspect that the,
that the ability to get into top schools
may largely depend on coming from an affluent family,
having a favorable back, family background,
social, cultural, economic advantages and so on?
I mean economic, but yes, social, cultural,
all of those advantages for sure.
Someone did a study of
the 146 selective colleges and universities
in the United States.
And they looked at the
students in those colleges and universities
to try to find out what their background was,
their economic background.
What percentage do you think come from the bottom quarter
of the income scale?
You know what the figure is?
Only 3% of students at
the most selective colleges and universities
come from poor backgrounds.
Over 70% come from affluent families.
Let's go one step further then
and try to address Mike's challenge.
Rawls actually has two arguments, not one,
in favor of his principles of justice,
and in particular of the difference principle.
One argument is the official argument.
What would be chosen behind the veil of ignorance?
Some people challenge that argument saying,
maybe people would want to take their chances.
Maybe people would be gamblers behind the veil of ignorance,
hoping that they would wind up on top.
That's one challenge that has been put to Rawls.
But backing up the argument from the original position
is a second argument.
And that is a straightforwardly moral argument.
And it goes like this.
It says,
the distribution of income and wealth and opportunities
should not be based on factors
for which people can claim no credit.
It shouldn't be based on factors that are arbitrary
from a moral point of view.
Rawls illustrates this by considering
several rival theories of justice.
He begins with the theory of justice
that most everyone these days would reject.
A feudal aristocracy.
What's wrong with the allocation of life prospects
in a feudal aristocracy?
Rawls says,
well, the thing that's obviously wrong about it
is that people's life prospects are determined
by the accident of birth.
Are you born to a noble family
or to the family of peasants and serfs?
And that's it.
You can't rise.
It's not your doing where you wind up
or what opportunities you have.
But that's arbitrary from a moral point of view.
And so that objection to feudal aristocracy,
leads and historically has led people to say,
careers should be open to talents.
There should be formal equality of opportunity
regardless of the accident of birth.
Every person should be free to strive,
to work, to apply for any job in the society.
And then, if you open up jobs
and you allow people to apply,
and to work as hard as they can,
then the results are just.
So it's more or less the libertarian system
that we've discussed in earlier weeks.
What does Rawls think about this?
He says it's an improvement.
It's an improvement because it doesn't take as fixed
the accident of birth.
But even with formal equality of opportunity,
the libertarian conception doesn't extend that
doesn't extend its insight far enough.
Because if you let everybody run the race,
everybody can enter the race,
but some people start at different starting points,
that race isn't going to be fair.
Intuitively, he says,
the most obvious injustice of this system
is that it permits distributive shares
to be improperly influenced by factors
arbitrary from a moral point of view,
such as whether you got a good education or not,
whether you grew up in a family that supported you
and developed in you a work ethic
and gave you the opportunities.
So that suggests moving to a system of fair
equality of opportunity,
and that's really the system that Mike was advocating
earlier on.
What we might call a merit-based system,
a meritocratic system.
In a fair meritocracy,
the society sets up institutions
to bring everyone to the same starting point
before the race begins.
Equal educational opportunities,
Head Start programs, for example,
support for schools in impoverished neighborhoods,
so that everyone, regardless of their family background,
has a genuinely fair opportunity,
everyone starts from the same starting line.
Well, what does Rawls think about
the meritocratic system?
Even that, he says,
doesn't go far enough in remedying
or addressing
the moral arbitrariness
of the natural lottery.
Because if you bring everyone
to the same starting point,
and begin the race,
who's going to win the race?
Who would win?
To use the runner's example.
The fastest runners would win.
But is it their doing
that they happen to be blessed
with the athletic prowess to run fast?
So Rawls says,
even the principle of meritocracy,
where you bring everyone to the same starting point,
may eliminate the influence of social contingencies
and upbringing,
but it still permits the distribution
of wealth and income to be determined
by the natural distribution
of abilities and talents.
And so he thinks
that the principle of eliminating
morally arbitrary influences
in the distribution of income and wealth
requires going beyond
what Mike favors,
the meritocratic system.
Now, how do you go beyond?
If you bring everyone to the same starting point,
and you're still bothered by the fact
that some are fast runners
and some are not fast runners,
what can you do?
Well, some critics
of a more egalitarian conception
say the only thing you can do
is handicap the fast runners.
Make them wear lead shoes.
But who wants to do that?
That would defeat the whole point
of running the race.
But Rawls says,
you don't have to have
a kind of leveling equality
if you want to go beyond
a meritocratic conception.
You permit,
you even encourage,
those who may be gifted
to exercise their talents.
But what you do,
is you change the terms
on which people are entitled
to the fruits of the exercise
of those talents.
And that really is what
the difference principle is.
You establish a principle that says,
people may benefit
from their good fortune,
from their luck in the genetic lottery,
but only on terms
that work to the advantage
of the least well-off.
And so, for example,
Michael Jordan can make
$31 million,
but only under a system
that taxes away
a chunk of that
to help those who lack
the basketball skills
that he's blessed with.
Likewise, Bill Gates,
he can make his billions,
but he can't think that he somehow
morally deserves those billions.
Those who have been favored by nature
may gain from their good fortune,
but only on terms
that improve the situation
of those who have lost out.
That's the difference principle.
And it's an argument
from moral arbitrariness.
Rawls claims that if you're bothered
by basing distributive shares
on factors arbitrary
from a moral point of view,
you don't just reject
a feudal aristocracy
for a free market.
You don't even rest content
with a meritocratic system
that brings everyone
to the same starting point.
You set up a system
where everyone,
including those at the bottom,
benefit from the exercise
of the talents
held by those
who happen to be lucky.
What do you think?
Is that persuasive?
Who finds that argument
unpersuasive,
the argument
from moral arbitrariness?
Yes?
I think that in the egalitarian
proposition,
the more talented people,
I think it's very optimistic
to think that they would still
work really hard
even if they knew
that part of what they made
would be given away.
So I think that the only way
for the more talented people
to exercise their talents
to the best of their ability
is in the meritocracy.
And in a meritocracy,
what's your name?
Kate.
Does it bother you?
And Mike, does it bother you?
I think that the more talented
people,
the more talented they are,
the more talented they are
in the meritocracy.
And I think that
in a meritocratic system,
even with fair equality
of opportunity,
people get ahead,
people get rewards
that they don't deserve
simply because they happen
to be naturally gifted.
What about that?
I think that it is arbitrary
and obviously it's arbitrary,
but I think that they're,
that correcting for it
would be detrimental
and unlike...
Because it would reduce
the value of the race.
Yeah.
Mike, what do you say?
We're all sitting in this room
and we have undeserved,
we have undeserved glory
of some sort
so you should not be satisfied
with the process of your life
because you have not created
any of this.
And I think from a standpoint
of not just this room
us being upset,
but from a societal standpoint,
we should have some kind of
a gut reaction to that feeling
that, you know,
the guy who runs the race,
he doesn't,
he actually harms us
as opposed to maybe makes me
run that last 10 yards faster
and that makes the guy behind me
run 10 yards faster
and the guy behind him
10 yards faster.
All right, so Mike,
let me ask you,
you talked about effort before.
Effort.
Do you think when people work hard
to get ahead and succeed
that they deserve the rewards
that go with effort?
Isn't that the idea
behind your defense of...
I mean, of course,
bring Michael Jordan here,
I'm sure you can get him,
and have him come
and defend himself
about why he makes $31 million
and I think what you're going
to realize is his life
was a very, very tough one
to get to the top
and that we are very,
very proud of him
for basically being
the majority oppressing
the minority in a different light.
It's very easy to pick on him.
All right.
Very easy.
Effort.
You know what?
All right, you've got...
I've got a few.
You've persuaded a lot of people.
I've got a few,
but that's about it.
Effort.
You know what
Raul's answer to that is?
Even the effort
that some people expend,
conscientious driving,
the work ethic,
even effort depends a lot
on fortunate results
and family circumstances
for which you,
we,
can claim no credit.
Now, let's...
Wait, we're going to let...
Let's do the test.
Let's do a test here.
Never mind economic class.
Those differences
are very significant.
Put those aside.
Psychologists say that birth order
makes a lot of difference
in work ethic,
striving, effort.
How many here...
Raise your hand,
those of you here
who are first in birth order.
I am too, by the way.
Mike, I noticed you raised your hand.
If the case
for the meritocratic conception
is that effort should be rewarded,
doesn't Raul's answer
have a point
that even effort,
striving,
work ethic
is largely shaped
even by birth order?
Is it your doing?
Mike, is it your doing
that you were first in birth order?
Then why, Raul says,
of course not.
So why should income and wealth
and opportunities in life
be based on birth order?
Why should the birth order
be based on factors
arbitrary from a moral point of view?
That's a challenge that he puts
to market societies,
but also
to those of us
at places like this.
A question to think about
for next time.
A justice of the United States Supreme Court.
What do they make?
It's just under $200,000.
But there's another judge
who makes a lot more
than Sandra Day O'Connor.
Do you know who it is?
Judge Judy.
How did you know that?
Do you know how much she makes?
$25 million.
Now,
is that just?
Is it fair?
We ended last time
with that remarkable poll.
Do you remember?
The poll about birth order?
What percentage of people
in this room
raised their hands?
Was it
to say that they were the first born?
75, 80 percent?
And what was the significance of that
if you're thinking about these theories
of distributive justice?
Remember,
we were discussing
three different theories
of distributive justice.
Three different ways
of answering the question,
how should individuals,
how should the population,
how should income and wealth
and opportunities
and the good things in life
be distributed?
And so far,
we've looked at the libertarian answer
that says the just system
of distribution
is a system of free exchange,
a free market economy,
against a background
of formal equality,
which simply means
that jobs and careers
are open to anyone.
We've looked at the libertarian answer,
which is that
the system of just distribution
is the one that results
from free exchange,
free exchange,
free exchange.
Then,
Rawls says
that the free market economy
is the one that results
from free exchange,
free exchange.
Rawls says
this represents an improvement
over aristocratic
and caste systems
because everyone can compete
for every job,
careers,
open talents.
And beyond that,
the just distribution
is the one that results
from free exchange,
is formal equality, jobs open to everyone, the
result is not going to be fair. It
will be biased in favor of those
who happen to be born to affluent families,
who happen to have the benefit
of good educational opportunities. And that
accident of birth is not a just
basis for distributing life chances. And so
many people who notice this unfairness, Rawls
argues, are led to embrace a system
of fair equality of opportunity.
That leads to the meritocratic system.
Fair equality of opportunity. But Rawls says,
even if you bring everyone to the
same starting point in the race, what's
going to happen? Who's going to win? The
fastest runners. So once you're troubled
by basing distributive shares on morally
arbitrary contingencies, you should, if
you reason it through, be careful
about what you're doing. And that's what he
carried all the way to what Rawls calls
the democratic conception, a
more egalitarian conception of distributive
justice that he defines by the difference
principle. Now he doesn't say that the
only way to remedy or to
compensate for differences in natural talents and
abilities is to have a kind of
leveling equality, a guaranteed equality of outcome.
But he does say there's another way
to deal with these contingencies. People may gain,
may benefit from their good fortune, but only
on terms that work to the advantage of the
least well-off. And so we can test how
this theory actually works by thinking about some
pay differentials that arise in our society.
What does the average school teacher make
in the United States, do you suppose?
Roughly?
It's a little more, 40, 42,000. What about
David Letterman? How much do you think David
Letterman makes? More than a school teacher?
Thirty-one million dollars. David Letterman. Is
that fair? That David Letterman, the
David Letterman makes that much more than
a school teacher. Well, Rawls' answer would
be, it depends whether the basic structure of
society is designed in such a way that
Letterman's thirty-one million dollars is subject
to taxation so that some of those
earnings are taken to work for the advantage
of the least well-off. One other example of
a pay differential.
A justice of the United States Supreme Court.
What do they make? It's just under $200,000.
Here's Sandra Day O'Connor, for example. There
she is. But there's another judge who makes
a lot more than Sandra Day
O'Connor. Do you know who it is?
Judge Judy.
Judge Judy. How did you know that? You
watch? You know, but you've heard. You're right.
Judge Judy. Do you know how much
she makes? There she is. Twenty-five, twenty-five million
dollars. Now, is that just? Is it fair?
Well, the answer is it depends whether the basic
structure of society is designed in such a
way that the tax credit system is designed
to support the most well-off.
Now, let's talk about this.
Let's talk about the basic structure of society.
I'm going to talk about this in a different way.
You know, I'm going to talk
about this in a different way.
I'm going to talk about this in a different way.
Let's talk about this in a different way.
and a TV judge, the
one Marcus watches all the time.
What I want to do
now is return to these theories
and to examine the objections
to Rawls' more egalitarian theory,
the difference principle.
There are at least three objections.
To Rawls' difference principle.
One of them came up last time in the discussion,
and a number of you raised this worry.
What about incentives?
Isn't there the risk if taxes
reach 70, 80, 90% marginal rate
that Michael Jordan won't play basketball?
That David Letterman won't do late night comedy?
Or that CEOs will go
into some other line of work?
Now, who among those who are defenders of Rawls,
who has an answer to this objection
about the need for incentives?
Yes.
Go ahead.
Stand up.
Thank you.
Rawls' idea is that there should,
there should only be so much difference
that it helps the least well-off the most.
So if there's too much equality,
then the least well-off might not
be able to watch late night TV
or might not have a job
because their CEO doesn't want to work.
So you need to find the correct balance
where taxation still leaves enough incentive
for the least well-off to benefit from the talents.
Good.
And what's your name?
Tim.
All right.
So Tim is saying, in effect,
that Rawls takes account of incentives
and could allow for pay differentials
and for some adjustment in the tax rate
to take account of incentives.
But, Tim points out,
the standpoint from which
the question of incentives needs to be considered
is not the effect on the
total size of the economic pie,
but instead from the standpoint of the effect
of the economic pie.
Of the economic pie.
Of incentives or disincentives
on the well-being of those at the bottom.
Right?
Good.
Thank you.
I think that is what Rawls would say.
In fact, if you look in section 17,
where he describes the difference principle,
he allows for incentives.
The naturally advantaged are not to gain.
Merely because they are more gifted,
but only to cover the cost of training and education
and for using their endowments
in ways that help the less fortunate as well.
So you can have incentives.
You can adjust the tax rate
if taking too much from David Letterman
or from Michael Jordan
or from Bill Gates
winds up actually hurting those at the bottom.
That's the test.
So incentives,
that's not a decisive objection
against Rawls' difference principle.
But there are two weightier,
more difficult objections.
One of them
comes
from defenders of a meritocratic conception.
The argument that says,
what about effort?
What about people working hard,
having a right to what they earn
because they've deserved it,
they've worked hard for it?
That's the objection from effort and moral desert.
Then there's another objection
that comes from libertarians.
And this objection has to do with reasserting the idea,
of self-ownership.
Doesn't the difference principle,
by treating our natural talents and endowments
as common assets,
doesn't that violate the idea that we own ourselves?
Now, let me deal first
with the objection that
comes from the libertarian direction.
Milton Friedman writes,
in his book, Free to Choose,
life is not fair.
And it's tempting to believe
that government can rectify
what nature has spawned.
But his answer is,
the only way to try to rectify that
is to have a leveling equality of outcome,
everyone finishing the race at the same point,
and the government
is going to have to be able to do that.
And that would be a disaster.
This is an easy argument to answer.
And Rawls addresses it
in one of the most powerful passages,
I think, of the theory of justice.
It's in section 17.
The natural distribution,
and here he's talking about the natural distribution
of talents and endowments,
is neither just nor unjust.
Nor is it unjust that persons are born into society
at some particular position.
These are simply natural facts.
What is just and unjust
is the way that institutions deal with these facts.
That's his answer
to libertarian laissez-faire economists
like Milton Friedman who say,
life is unfair, but get over it.
Get over it, and let's see if we can
at least maximize the benefits that flow from it.
But the more powerful libertarian objection to Rawls
is not from the libertarian economists
like Milton Friedman.
It's from the argument about self-ownership,
developed, as we saw, in Nozick.
And from that point of view,
yes, it might be a good thing
to create Head Start programs
and public schools
so that everyone can go to a decent school
and start the race at the same starting line.
That might be good.
But if you tax people to create public schools,
if you tax people
against their will,
you coerce them.
It's a form of theft.
If you take some of Letterman's 31 million,
tax it away to support
public schools
against his will,
the state is really doing no better
than stealing from him.
It's coercion.
And the reason is,
we have to think of ourselves
as owning our talents and endowments.
Because otherwise, we're back to just using people
and coercing people.
That's the libertarian reply.
What's Rawls's answer?
What's Rawls's answer to that objection?
He doesn't address the idea of self-ownership directly.
But the effect,
the moral weight of his argument
for the difference principle is,
maybe we don't own ourselves
in that thoroughgoing sense after all.
Now, he says this doesn't mean
that the state
is an owner in me
in the sense that it can simply
commandeer my life.
Because remember, the first principle
we would agree to behind the veil of ignorance
is the principle of equal basic liberties.
Freedom of speech, religious liberty,
freedom of conscience, and the like.
So the only respect
in which the idea of self-ownership must give way
comes when we're thinking about whether
I own myself in the sense that
I have a privileged claim
on the benefits that come
from the exercise of my talents
in a market economy.
And Rawls says, on reflection, we don't.
We can define that as,
we can defend rights,
we can respect the individual,
we can uphold human dignity
without embracing the idea of self-possession.
That, in effect, is his reply
to the libertarian.
I want to turn now
to his reply to the defender
of a meritocratic conception,
who invokes effort
as the basis of moral desert.
People who work hard to develop their talents
deserve the benefits
that come from the exercise of their talents.
Well, we've already seen
the beginning of Rawls's answer
to that question,
and it goes back to that
poll we took about birth order.
His first answer is,
even the work ethic,
even the willingness to strive conscientiously,
depends on all sorts of family circumstances
and social and cultural contingencies
for which we can claim no credit.
You can't claim credit for the fact that
you, most of you, most of us,
happen to be first in birth order,
and that for some complex psychological and social reasons,
that seems to be associated
with striving, with achieving, with effort.
That's one answer.
There's a second answer.
Those of you who invoke effort,
you don't really believe
that moral desert attaches to effort.
Take two construction workers.
One is strong and can
raise four walls in an hour.
Without even breaking a sweat.
And another construction worker is small and scrawny,
and has to spend three days
to do the same amount of work.
No defender of meritocracy
is going to look at the effort
of that weak and scrawny construction worker
and say, therefore, he deserves to make more.
So it isn't really effort.
This is the second reply.
To the meritocratic claim.
It isn't really effort
that the defender of meritocracy
believes is the moral basis
of distributive shares.
It's contribution.
How much do you contribute?
But contribution takes us straight back
to our natural talents and abilities.
Not just effort.
And it's not our doing,
how we came into the possession of those talents
in the first place.
All right, suppose you accepted these arguments.
That effort isn't everything.
That contribution matters
from the standpoint of the meritocratic conception.
That effort even isn't our own doing.
Does that mean...
The objection continues.
Does that mean that according to Rawls,
moral desert has nothing to do
with distributive justice?
Well, yes.
Distributive justice is not about moral desert.
Now, here, Rawls introduces
an important and a tricky distinction.
It's between moral desert on the one hand
and entitlements to legitimate expectations
on the other.
What is the difference between
moral deserts and entitlements?
Consider two different games.
A game of chance and a game of skill.
Take a game of pure chance.
Say I play the Massachusetts State Lottery
and my number comes up.
I'm entitled to my winnings.
But even though I'm entitled to my winnings,
there's no sense in which,
because it's just a game of luck,
no sense in which I morally deserve
to win in the first place.
That's an entitlement.
Now, contrast the lottery
with a different kind of game,
a game of skill.
Now, imagine the Boston Red Sox
winning the World Series.
When they win,
they're entitled to the trophy,
but it can be always asked
of a game of skill,
did they deserve to win?
It's always possible in principle
to distinguish
what someone's entitled to
under the rules
and whether they deserve to win
in the first place.
That's an antecedent standard,
moral desert.
Now, Rawls says distributive justice
is not a matter of moral desert,
though it is a matter of entitlements
to legitimate expectations.
Here's where he explains it.
A just scheme answers
to what men are entitled to.
It satisfies
their legitimate expectations
as founded upon social institutions.
But what they are entitled to
is not proportional to,
nor dependent on,
their intrinsic worth.
The principles of justice
that regulate the basic structure
do not mention moral desert,
and there is no tendency
for distributive shares
to correspond to it.
Why does Rawls make this distinction?
What morally is at stake?
One thing morally at stake
is the whole question of effort
that we've already discussed.
But there's a second contingency,
a second source of moral arbitrariness
that goes beyond the question
of whether it's to my credit
that I have the talents
that enable me to get ahead.
And that has to do with the contingency
that I live in a society
that happens to be a society
that is able to prize my talents.
The fact that David Letterman
lives in a society that puts a great premium,
puts a great value
on a certain type of smirky joke,
that's not his doing.
He's lucky that he happens to live
in such a society.
But this is a second contingency.
This isn't something that we can claim credit for.
Even if I had sole unproblematic claim
to my talents and to my effort,
it would still be the case
that the benefits I get
from exercising those talents
depend on factors
that are arbitrary from a moral point of view.
What my talents will reap in a market economy,
what does that depend on?
What other people happen to want or like
in this society?
It depends on the law of supply and demand.
That's not my doing.
Certainly not the basis for moral desert.
What counts as contributing
depends on the qualities
that this or that society happens to prize.
Most of us are fortunate to possess,
in large measure, for whatever reason,
the qualities that our society
happens to prize.
The qualities that enable us
to provide what society wants.
In a capitalist society,
it helps to have entrepreneurial drive.
In a bureaucratic society,
it helps to get on easily and smoothly
with superiors.
In a mass democratic society,
it helps to look good on television
and to speak in short, superficial sound bites.
In a litigious society,
it helps to go to law school
and to have the talents
to do well on LSATs.
But none of this is our doing.
Suppose that we with our talents inhabited
not our society, technologically advanced,
highly litigious,
but a hunting society or a warrior society.
What would become of our talents then?
They wouldn't get us very far.
No doubt some of us would develop other talents.
Some of us would develop others.
But would we be less worthy?
Would we be less virtuous?
Would we be less meritorious
if we lived in that kind of society
rather than in ours?
Rawls' answer is no.
We might make less money,
and properly so.
But while we would be entitled to less,
we would be no less worthy,
no less deserving than we are now.
And here's the point.
The same could be said of those in our society
who happen to hold less prestigious positions,
who happen to have fewer of the talents
that our society happens to reward.
So here's the moral import of the distinction
between moral desert and entitlements
to legitimate expectations.
We are entitled to the benefits,
but the rules of the game promise
for the exercise of our talents.
But it's a mistake and a conceit
to suppose that we deserve in the first place
a society that values the qualities
we happen to have in abundance.
Now we've been talking here
about income and wealth.
What about opportunities and honors?
What about the distribution of access,
of seats in elite colleges and universities?
It's true.
All of you, most of you first born,
worked hard, strived,
developed your talents to get here.
But Rawls asks, in effect,
what is the moral status of your claim?
To the benefits that attach
to the opportunities you have.
Are seats in colleges and universities
a matter, a kind of reward,
an honor for those who deserve them
because they've worked so hard?
Or are those seats,
those opportunities and honors
entitlements to legitimate expectations,
that depend for their justification
on those of us who enjoy them,
doing so in a way
that works to the benefit
of those at the bottom of society?
That's the question
that Rawls's difference principle poses.
It's a question that can be asked
of the earnings of Michael Jordan
and David Letterman
and Judge Judy,
but it's also a question that can be asked
of opportunities
to go to
the top colleges and universities.
And that's a debate
that comes out
when we turn to the question of affirmative action
next time.
Thank you.
Funding for this program
is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...